<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discouery of the vntruthes and slanders (against the true gouernement of the Church of Christ) contained in a sermon, preached the 8. [sic] of Februarie 1588. by D. Bancroft and since that time, set forth in print, with additions by the said authour. This short ansvver may serue for the clearing of the truth, vntill a larger confutation of the sermon be published.</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114383</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849608</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14765</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68566)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14765)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 196:2, 516:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discouery of the vntruthes and slanders (against the true gouernement of the Church of Christ) contained in a sermon, preached the 8. [sic] of Februarie 1588. by D. Bancroft and since that time, set forth in print, with additions by the said authour. This short ansvver may serue for the clearing of the truth, vntill a larger confutation of the sermon be published.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
                  <author>Bancroft, Richard, 1544-1610. Sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 9. of Februarie. Selections.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Penry.</note>
                  <note>A partial reprinting of and reply to: Bancroft, Richard. A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 9. of Februarie.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 1351 on UMI microfilm reel 196.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 196 (British Library copy) and at reel 516 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bancroft, Richard, 1544-1610. --  Sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 9. of Februarie --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14765:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14765:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVERY OF THE VNTRVTHES AND SLAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS (AGAINST THE TRVE GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of the Church of Chriſt) contained in a Sermon, preached the 8. of Februarie 1588. by D. Bancroft, and ſince that time, ſet forth in Print, with additions by the ſaid Authour.</p>
            <p>THIS SHORT ANSVVER MAY SERVE FOR THE CLEARING OF the truth, vntill a larger confutation of the Sermon be publiſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. PET. 2.1.2.3.</bibl>
But there were falſe Prophetes alſo among the people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euen as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, which priuilie ſhall bring in damnab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hereſies, euen denying the Lord that hath bought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, &amp; bring vpon themſelues ſwift da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. And many ſhall follow their damnable wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, by whom the way of truth ſhall be euell ſpoken of. And through couetouſnes, ſhall they with fained words, make marchandiſe of you, whoſe judgment long agon, is not farre of.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14765:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14765:2"/>
            <head>TO THE GODLIE INDIFFERENT Reader, judgement to diſcerne, and zeale to imbrace the truth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinke it no wonderful caſe beloued, to ſee the church of England ſo out of order at this day as our confuſions are altogether more in number, then the ha res of our head. For thoſe that will needes bee our Paſtors and ſpirituall fathers, are become beaſtes as the Prophet Ierem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaith, and haue not ſought the Lord. And therfore what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell is it, though we the poore ſheepe bee miſerablie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed not knowing whether to turne vs for any ſuccour. Our guides haue not onely miſled vs, but they are become wolues in ſtead of ſhepheards. So that we dare not ſhew our ſelues, for feare of their teeth, to ſeke any paſture but the bare feeding which they haue laid before vs. And if we ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pen our mouths, to ſue for the true ſhepheards and ouerſeers indeed vnto whoſe direction, we ought to be committed: The rage of theſe wolues is ſuch (thou ſeeſt) as this endeuor would almoſt be the price of our life. For if this requeſt were once granted, they ful wel perceiue, that they ſhould not haue ſo much as a place of a doore keeper within the ſheepefold of the Lord. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they euery way labour, to keepe vs in bondage. They hide the truth, &amp; will not ſuffer others to ſee the ſame. If the Lord in mercy, doe open the eies of any man, hee muſt not for his life, make it known that he hath ſeene the light, much leſſe, walke in the ſame, and wiſh others to follow him.</p>
            <p>They ſeeme at this day, to haue greater liberty, to wound the church, then any they had ſince the beginning of her Majeſties raign, and therfore ought the godly to enarme themſelues againſt them, now more then before. They make vſe of the time, and the oportunity which they haue gotten, to keepe the truth and the church in their bondage. VVonder not at it: for this is the very houre and power of darkenes, wherein they haue liberty to do no more yet, then the right hand of our God hath determined long before and when he hath accompliſhed his work, in mount Sion and Ieruſalem, then let them, and whoſoeuer fauour any of the ofspring of Romiſh Babell their mother, take heed vnto themſelues. In the beginning of her Majeſties raign, was the mouth of gods ſaints in England, filled with laughter, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theſe men labour to blot out all that ioy with the teares, if not with the bloud of the church. And in the meane time, her Majeſty wee are aſſured, is ignorant of the right caſe of the murthering concluſions, ſet vp againſt vs by theſe Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. Oh that it pleaſed the Lorde, that our courſe might bee examined by her highnes, and that ſhe would not ſuffer both our judges and our accuſers, to condemne vs for thoſe thinges, whereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſhall neuer bee able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince vs with any colour. If we muſt needs be perſecuted, yea, and die (for I ſee that the Prelates, and their complices meane no otherwiſe to be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then with the blotting out of our names from among men) would to God yet, wee might die by her hand, that is, beeing conuicted by her godlie lawes, to deſerue that which we are like to ſuffer For otherwiſe, I perſwade my ſelfe, we ſhould not be indamaged by her Majeſty except we were found to bee gilty of puniſhment, by the voyce of her good lawes. The enemies haue long ſince endeuoured, to prooue vs to be dangerous ſubjects and yet
<pb facs="tcp:14765:3"/>to this day, we are ready to defie them vnto their faces, and to maintaine our innocency both by the law of God, and the laws of this kingdome. Againſt which, Tertullus, the greateſt Atheiſt, &amp; cunningeſt lawier of all their crew was neuer able to prooue, that we haue any waies offended How violently they wreſt the lawes againſt vs, their ſoules (which I wiſh not) ſhall find it.</p>
            <p>The courſe which they haue taken to confute vs by writing, hath beene ſo gainles vnto them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we neuer ſaw their third anſwer in the cauſe. They haue indeed, like men being driuen vnto a hole, ſometimes made an irrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon vs, as they do daily in their Sermons, but when it coms to paſſe, that they muſt either ſtand vnto their cauſe, or ſuffer the ouerthrow, wee ſee not one of them, that wil abide the third encounter. And yet they ceaſe not, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to diſcouer themſelues, although they bring no other furniture with them then that which hath bene battered and made vnſeruiceable long ſince. M. Bancroft hath beene one of the laſt aduerſaries that wee haue ſeene, and yet hath he furniſhed himſelfe with no new artillery, but onely was content to borrow thoſe, wherewith the Archbiſhop loſt the field. For he hath nothing in a maner againſt vs in his whole Sermon, but ſuch thinges as haue bin an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered long ago by M. Cartwright, yea, his ſlaunders, and all for the moſt part (though he bee skilfull that way himſelfe) he hath borrowed either of D. VVhitgift, or of Doctor Coſins, in his anſwere to the Abſtract, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue bene already confuted. In conſideration whereof, I had thought him not worth the anſwering, were it not that I did ſee, the Lord to require at our handes, the juſtifiyng of his truth, as often as the ſame is called into queſtion, or any waies vnworthily handled.</p>
            <p>There haue bene others I ſuppoſe, that haue taken more paines with this inuectiue Sermon of his, I haue therefore left place vnto them, whoſoeuer they are, to publiſh that wherein they haue more fully and more largely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, the euill and vnreaſonable dealing of the Chaplaine. I haue exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned few or none of the teſtimonies of men brought in by him, the aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which that way might be had againſt him, I haue not taken, both becauſe I ſaw it not very material, that he ſhould be conuinced, to abuſe the writings of men, who is not aſhamed to offer iniurie vnto the holy ſcriptures of God, and alſo for as much, as it may be, others will indite him for that falſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his. If his cauſe be good, &amp; he able to defend it with truth &amp; vpright dealing, I haue ſhewed him the way to atchieue his purpoſe: And that is, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to father vpon vs ſuch thinges as we neuer maintained, nor yet to bring the teſtimonies of men to oppugn our concluſions, whoſe grounds he is not able to ſhake: but to ſet downe that which we holde indeed, and with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons rather to anſwere our premiſses, then with authorities to ſtrike at our concluſions. The contrary dealing, may colour and white line the breaches of his cauſe for a time, but in the end, it will prooue to be the ruine thereof. Vnconſcionable and ſophiſtical dealing, can neuer be able to ſtand any long time. He and his Maſters, would gladly beare the Magiſtrat in hand, that we deny the congregations in England, where the word is truly preached, and the ſacraments rightly adminiſtred, to be the viſible churches of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the truth is, that the Biſhops and not we, doe maintaine this error. Let the reader judge, whether I truly accuſe them by this which followeth.</p>
            <p>The viſible church of God whereſoeuer it bee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath the power of binding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd looſing annexed vnto it, as our ſauiour Chriſt teacheth vs. Mathew 18.
<pb facs="tcp:14765:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>which authority is ſo eſſentially tied vnto the viſible church, that whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this power is to bee found, there the church of Chriſt is alſo viſible,<note place="margin">Our Bb. are ſciſmatickes and deny the aſſemblie of England to be viſible church of God. booke of Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tins page 5. 6.</note> and whereſoeuer there is a viſible church, there this authority cannot bee denied to be. The which point that reuerend father, M. Iohn Fox teacheth more at large. Now the reader cannot be ignorant that our Biſhops wil neuer grant that the viſible congregations in England, ought to haue this power of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and looſing, for then ſhould they manifeſt themſelues to bee profeſſed tyrants. The crime therefore of Sciſme and Donatiſme, which M. Bancroft and the Prelates would faſten vpon vs, doth juſtly cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue vnto them ſelues. And if any of our poore brethren be caried away, to thinke otherwiſe of the congregations of England, which inioy the woorde truly preached, and the right vſe of the Sacrament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: VVe ceaſe not to pray that the Lord would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their iudgements. But woe bee vnto our Biſhops, which are the cauſe of this their ſtumbling, and maintainers of their error. For the pore brethren doe holde nothing in this point, but that which the learned fathers, as M. Bancroft calleth them haue decreed. And you ſhall ſee in this Treatiſe, that he ſeeth no reaſon, why Popery being now abolliſhed,<note place="margin">Sermon pag. 3,</note> wee ſhould not reply vppon the determinations of theſe fathers, as other men in time paſt of a: great iudgement as we are, haue done. Let our Biſhops then, and their vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, whiſper into the eare of the Magiſtrate what they will, it ſhall bee prooued in the end, that they are the ſciſmatickes and not we. It ſhall appear that they are growing to make a body of their owne, wherewith the church of God in a while (if they hold on their courſe) can haue no mote to do, then in times paſt in had with the ſciſmaticall Donatiſts.</p>
            <p>The deuill indeede hath within this twelmoneth, ſhewed himſelfe to bee grieuouſly wounded in their perſons, becauſe he hath raged ſo mightily, as theſe 32. yeares his furie was neuer ſeene ſo great againſt the truth as at this preſent. That vile and ſcurrilous Palmphlet,<note place="margin">An almond a Patrot.</note> latey ſuffered to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by their priuity (if not allowance) and in their defence doth euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that ſathan feeleth the power and ſway which he was wont to bear by vertue of the hierarchie, to be greatly weakned. And becauſe he feareth that his time vnder their gouernment cannot be long therefore he meaneth now to infect the aire at once, with all his contagions. The ſtrength which they get by ſuch leud and filthie ſtuffe, &amp; the diſcredit which thereby they worke either vnto the cauſe, or the men and women whome they ſuffer to bee ſo vnworthilie traduced, is not other then it were to bee wiſhed (that ſeeing they will needs be filthy) they would publiſh ſuch another booke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day: That then it might appeare indeede whoſe ſonnes they are. And this is all the confutation that I thinke, ſo godles, &amp; leud a ſcrole to deſerue.</p>
            <p>For thy ſelfe good reader, thou ſeeſt the time of triall to be now at hand, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at the doore. If thou meaneſt to be partaker of Chriſtes kingdome after this life: take heede, that neither the feare of men, nor the loue of the world draw thee to ſhrinke from any part of that truth, which the Lorde hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled in his word. The Lord ſaith, that whoſoeuer ſhall be aſhamed of him or his worde, that is, any part of his truth before men,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.26.</note> of him ſhall the ſonne of man be aſhamed, when he commeth in his glory. VVell, I thinke it now no time to dally with the Lord and his word, but let vs craue ſtrength at his hand, that we ſtand vnrebukeable, vnto the day of his appearance.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14765:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14765:4"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVERY OF THE VNTRVTHES, AND SLANDERS AGAINST Reformation, and the fauourers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, contained in D. Bancrofts Sermon.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFTS TEXT. 1. Iohn 4.1.</bibl> Dearely beloued, beleeue not euery ſpirite, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ie the ſpirites, whether they be of God: For many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bene the ancient cuſtome of Sathan and his inſtruments in all a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">I anſwere not the word, but the abuſe of the word.</note> to abuſe the holy worde, and name of God, as a ground vnto all their vngodly proceedings againſt the Lorde and his Saints: that there by, they might haue ſome colour of their perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and wicked attempts againſt the truth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof. That I bee not tedious in a matter too apparant, hence it is, that in all the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the holy Martyrs of Chriſt, by that Romane Tyrant: We ſee all their proceſſes to begin in the name of God, &amp; the accuſaſions laid to the charge of the Saints to bee ſo boulſtred out with the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of holy Scripture, as though the ſpirite of God had none to condemne of hereſie, ſciſme, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and treaſon, ſaue onely the members and meſſengers of Chriſt Ieſus. And therefore M. Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft, if you begin with Scripture, and as I may ſay, in the name of God, begin to ſpeake againſt God, againſt his bleſſed verity and people you doe but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14765:5"/>your kind, in treading the ſteppes of your predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours: You haue your forefathers, the Scribes and Phariſes, that Antichriſtian beaſt of Rome, his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Biſhops, Legates inquiſitors and all others, that haue coloured their garments, with the bloud of the Lords choſen, for your preſidents and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. The deluſion of your courſe could not bee ſo great, if you did ſhewe your ſelfe in your colours. Your Sermon declareth that your affection ſerueth you, rather to fight againſt the truth with fire and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, then by ſober writing, or ſpeaking, to ſtand in the defence of your cauſe.</p>
               <p>Well, you deale againſt falſe Prophetes, Sciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, giddy ſpirites, diſturbers of the church, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to her Maieſties eſtate and prerogatiue. And wee on the otherſide, that fauour reformation, doe from the bottome of our hearts entreat and beſeech the eternall God, ſpeedily to conuert and turne all ſuch, if they be his, or els with ſpeed to ouerthrowe them in his fierce wrath. And as for our ſelues in particular, if we, who in ſincerity ſeeke the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of England; be either falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; Sciſmatiques, giddy ſpirits, diſturbers of the Church, enemies vnto her Maieſties eſtate or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we do without exception, entreat the Lorde in his fierie wrath and anger, euen this hower, to make vs viſible monuments, of his great indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both in this life, and in the day of the Lord Ieſus, &amp; roote the memory of vs and ours, out of the Church and kingdome of England for euer: that our moſt deare Soueraigne Queene Elizabeth, may continue and end her daies, not onely in the quietnes of her own
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14765:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſcience, but alſo in the coniunction, quietnes, and vnion of the hearts of all her Subiects and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And wee offer, not onely to cleare our ſelues, by theſe our voluntary proteſtations, made in the name and preſence of the great God of heauen and erth, but euen by ſhewing the goodnes of our cauſe according vnto the worde, and anſwering whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the aduerſary bringeth againſt vs. And what can wee doe more? Let vs then M. Bancroft ſee what you can ſay of vs, or our cauſe Here I omit, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer in your whol Sermon is impertinent vnto us, againſt whome you eſpecially deale, and come to the eight page thereof, where at the firſt meeting, you doe very brotherly ſalute vs, by the names of falſe Prophets, though of your courteſie, your care not much if you omit the name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFT. Pag. 8. line. 10.</bibl> Laſtly, they are falſe Prophetes, who do peruert the meaning of the Scriptures, for the maintenance and defence of any falſe doctrine, ſciſme, of hereſie. Herof you know, I might giue you many examples. I pray you beare with me if I ſet downe, one as ſtrange in my opinion, as any to be found in a matter of no great importance. The name of falſe prophets, I am content in diuers reſpects to ſuppreſſe. The matter it ſelfe, which I meane, ſtandeth in this ſort. There are many nowe a daies who doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that when Chriſt vſed theſe wordes: DTC ECCLESIAE.<note place="margin">Math. 18</note> He meant hereby to eſtabliſh in the Church foreuer, the ſame plot and forme of Eccleſiaſticall Gouernement to be en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct in euery pariſh which Moſes by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> counſell, appointed in mount Sinay:<note place="margin">Numb. 11.</note> and which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> was did imitate in their particular Sinagogues.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> read your Sermon, will beare you witnes, that you are ſufficiently able, to afforde your auditours an example of a falſe teacher: And yet it were hard, to account all thoſe to be falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14765:6"/>(without exception) who peruert the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worde, to the maintenaunce of euery point of falſe doctrine. For we know, that many of the true Miniſters of God, haue in the error of their iudgement, held ſome points of vnſound doctrine, and peruerted the meaning of the holy ſcripture for the maintenance of the ſame. To ſpeake nothing of Cyprian, Chriſoſtome, Ierome, Auguſtme, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, Origen and Barnard who haue had euery one of them their blemiſhes, and wreſted the word for the defence thereof: that worthy man of God, M. Luther you know, hath deliuered vniuſtifiable and falſe doctrine, concerning the manner of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the thing ſignified, to wit Chriſt Ieſus, in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: and as it may bee truly ſayde, hee hath peruerted many places of the worde, for the maintenance of this his error, yet M. Bancroft, I thinke you will not inrolle him in the catalogue of falſe Prophets: Wherefore, if I denied the ground and principle of your reaſon, and ſent you again vnto your note book, for a better deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a falſe Prophet, I ſhould do nothing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto equity and reaſon. But I meane not to ſtand with you in a maner of ſo ſmall moment: ſeeing, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially you do by this your diſcription, teach the reader, what account he is to make of you, and your brethren of the ſame crewe, who daily in your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and writings, do wreſt, peruert, and abuſe the ſacred word of God, for the maintenaunce of moſt falſe and pernicious doctrine, whereof it may bee, ſome thing ſhall be ſpoken hereafter.</p>
               <p>But I pray you, who are they that expound the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14765:6"/>words of our ſauiour Chriſt. Mat. 18. Dic eccleſiae: Tell the Church, to bee referred to the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call gouernment, which Moſes by Iethroes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell appointed in mount Sinai? you ſay they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, why then did you not name one of them, or quote the writings of ſome one of them? Euen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, becauſe you are not able to father this abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie vpon none of thoſe, whome you would gladly beare the world in hand to be the maintainers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note place="margin">A godleſſe and ſlanderous ſhift of M. Bancro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And heere the reader is to bee aduertiſed, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many ſhiftes, which you haue to obſcure the truth, delude your readers and auditors, and to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour your ſlanderous vntruthes, there is one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you make a ſpeciall vſe, and that is to charge vs with the defence of ſuch points as wee neuer held: Thinking it ſufficient for you to ſay, that there are many now a daies who affirme, that when our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, &amp;c. Whereas the error, as you haue ſet it downe, is ſo abſurd and ſenceleſſe, and ſmelleth of ſuch groſſe ignorance, as I aſſure my ſelfe, that none who haue written in the cauſe of reformation ſince the beginning of her maieſties raign, vnto this how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, could bee ſo groſlye ouerſeene, as to conceiue, much leſſe holde and maintaine any ſuch thing as you haue vttered. For firſt, the officers appointed. Num. 11. (and I beſeech the reader to marke) were not ordained at mount Sinai,<note place="margin">Not at mount Sinai</note> as you haue ſet down, but (as the holy Ghoſt expreſly noteth) at Kibroth Hataauah,<note place="margin">Numb. 11.</note> which was 3. daies iorney from mount Sinai: compare Numb. 10.33. with Numb. 11 24.34 and 33.16. and Deut. 1.1. And therefore it is very abſurd, to aduouch that the 70. Elders, mencioned
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14765:7"/>Num. 11. were ordained at mount Sinai: and it is no leſſe falſe to giue our,<note place="margin">Not at the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Iethro</note> that theſe were the officers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Moſes at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of Iethro. For Iethroes aduiſe was put in execution,<note place="margin">Exod. 18.12. &amp; 40.17.</note> before the erecting of the Tabernacle, euen in the firſt year of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of Aegypt. The ordinance of the 70. elders, taken in hand after the ſetting vp of the Tabernaele,<note place="margin">Exod. 40.17. Numb. 10.11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> &amp; after the 20. day of the 2. moneth of the 2. yeare. Againe, the gouernours in Kibroth-Hataauah were but 70. or at the moſt 72. in number: the other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the counſel of Iethro, being gouerners of 1000. gouernors of 100. gouernors of 50. &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of 10. muſt needs exceed that number by many degrees.<note place="margin">Not eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</note> Laſtly, (which is your 3. ſlanderous abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie) who told you that the gouernment ordained in the 11. of Numbers, was Eccleſiaſticall. The very place it ſelfe, and all the circumſtances thereof doe prooue it to bee ciuill: And ſo our men that haue written of this argument would haue taught you,<note place="margin">Maſter Cornel. Bertram de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialud. cap. 6.</note> if you had ſought the trueth of the cauſe out of their writings. The holy ſtory it ſelfe, maketh the matter to bee out of controuerſie, which is this in effect. Numb. 11. There grew an vniuerſall murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, becauſe they had not fleſh to eat. The authoritie of the rulers ouer thouſands, rulers of hundreths, &amp;c. ordained by the aduiſe of Iethro, reached not beyond the number allotted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: So that the defection of the people being generall, (and it may bee, many of their rulers ioyned with them) they would not haue an anſwere, nor bee pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified by the inferior officers, but they come to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the chiefe gouernor, &amp; would haue him to giue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14765:7"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fleſh: Moſes being ſore vexed with the outcries againſt him, expoſtulateth with the Lord, thinking himſelfe to be hardly delt with, that there was none apointed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſtraining of the general <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>itude, but he himſelfe alone: Herupon the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to gather 70. of the Elders of Iſraell,<note place="margin">Verſe. 16.</note> ſuch (ſaith the text) as hee knew, to be governors of the people, &amp; the Lord would appoint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as aſſiſtants with him, to take the generall charge of the people, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the multitude would not be ruled by their inferior officers, as the rulers of 1000. &amp;c. theſe 70. elders ſhould be armed by the Lord, with authority and gifts, to beare the burthen with him, and it was peformed accordingly.</p>
               <p>Now M. Bancroft, for whoſe aſſiſtance were theſe Elders appointed? the word expreſly ſetteth down, that they were to aſſiſt Moſes: and therefore the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wherunto they were ordeined were ciuil; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they had bin eccleſiaſtical, they ſhould haue bin appointed helpers vnto Aaron. &amp; not vnto Moſes. For Moſes at this time was no more to intermedle with the prieſthood, becauſe Aaron &amp; his ſons,<note place="margin">Num. 16.10. Exod. 28.1.</note> were now conſecrated thervnto, &amp; the tribe of Leui allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to aſſiſt Aaron, euen to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge with him of the whole congregation,<note place="margin">Numb 3.7.</note> in reſpect of the tabernacle The laſt time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer Moſes dealt in the office of the prieſthood, was at the conſecration of Aaron &amp; his ſons, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time that Aaron was receued in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office, Moſes neuer medled with it any more.<note place="margin">Leu 8.90. Exod. 28.1. &amp; 29.44. &amp; 38.44. &amp; 30.7. Leuit. 1.5. &amp; cap. 8. &amp; 9. Num. 16.10. Num. 11.23.</note> So the cauſe is to clear, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they who were appointed to aſſiſt Moſes, &amp; not Aaron, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ciuil &amp; eccleſiaſtical ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. Where it is ſaid, than the 70. Elders prophiſied,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14765:8"/>it can no more proue them to belong to the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the church, then the like gift beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Saule,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 10.10:</note> can make him a church-officer.</p>
               <p>Seeing then M. Bancroft, the platforme of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, whereof you ſpeake, was neither appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at mount Siuai, nor by the counſell of Iethro, nor yet ordained for the regiment of the Church, but for the vſe of the ciuill ſtate, and ſeeing you can father this expoſition vpon none of theſe, whom af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward you call the cleargie and layitie factions, the conſequent is, that your owne ignoraunce in the cauſe of Chriſts gouernement which you oppugne, hath coyned vs this moſt vnlearned and ſenceleſſe expoſition: wherein you doe no more I grant, then that which is the common cuſtome of all your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: And that is, to imagine that theſe, who by the goodnes of God are ſeen in this cauſe, can bring no better reaſons for the defence of the ſame, then you whoſe ignoraunce therein is manifeſt and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous vnto vnto all men. And indeed for your part M. Bancroft, if you had any modeſty in you, &amp; ſhame of the world, (to omitte the conſcience and ſound feare of God, which ought to be in a Miniſter of the Goſpell as you would bee accounted) you would giue your ſelfe little reſt, vntill either you had na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs ſome of theſe very many, who affirme as you haue ſet downe, or make open confeſſion of your great ignorance in that cauſe, whereunto you haue beene alwaies ſo great an enemy. The reader may well know, that you haue ſet downe theſe thinges, rather of meere ignorance, then of ſingle malice on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe otherwiſe, you that are ſo ready to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14765:8"/>aduantage againſt your aduerſaries, and their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, would haue bene glad to haue found ſo many breaches in one poore reaſon of theirs: And though you would neuer ſo faine auoid this blot of your inſufficiency, yet your owne words following do witneſſe, that you haue ſpoken of the cauſe, euen according vnto the deep knowledge that you haue thereof, where you ſay that the Iewes in their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sinagogues, did imitate this gouernement or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Moſes in mount Sinai at the counſell of Iethro: As though, euery particuler Sinagogue of the Iewes could affoord 70. elders that were know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to be the gouernors of the people, to attend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the regiment of the Church? It appeares that you are well ſeene, either in the ciuill or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call politie of the Iewes, which appoint theſe elders vnto their particuler Sinagogs. You might as well ſaye, that wee in England in the gouernement of our particuler pariſhes, by Church-wardens and Side-men, doe reſemble the maieſtie that is in the aſſembly of Star chamber or at the Counſel table, as that the Iewes in their particuler Sinagogues, did imitate the gouernement of the 70. Elders: who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned in authoritie with Moſes, are manifeſted to bee the higheſt ciuill officers, that were in all the congregation of Iſrael, and both before and after the captiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, they are ſaide by the learned, to haue the higheſt authority in the Common-wealth of the Iewes, next vnto the ſupreame Magiſtrate. If you had bene but meanely ſeene in Ioſephus (to omitte other writers) you could not haue beene ignorant of this point. The name Elder it may be, is that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14765:9"/>you, thinking belike, that whereſoeuer wee read of any called Elders in the Scriptures, wee preſently take the place, as making for the Elderſhip vnder the Goſpell. Wee thinke farre otherwiſe then ſo, becauſe wee finde the Gouernours of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth,<note place="margin">Reade Geneſis 50.7. Ioſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 6.11.</note> as well as the rulers of the Church; to be called Elders by the ſpirit of God.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer then you ſay of falſe Prophets, (as you ſpeake much of them in your Sermons) the reader ſeeth, that at your firſt aſſault of the cauſe of Chriſts Gouernement, you haue manifeſted your ſelfe to bee of their number, that ſpeake euill of the thinges they knowe not, which the holy Ghoſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to be a marke of theſe falſe teachers,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.13.</note> by whom the way of truth in the latter ages, ſhould bee euill ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>But heere you will ſaye, that wee ground ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the proofe of the Elderſhippe vppon the place of Math. 18. Tell the Church, &amp;c. and that wee bring in the Iewiſhe Sinagogue for ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this queſtion. True it is, wee doe ſo: And becauſe you neither knowe, as it appeareth, what wee inferre, nor weare able to aunſwere them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made knowen vnto you therefore you did wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to ſet downe in our name, your owne abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which of themſelues, with out any confuter, deſire for ſhame to be buried vnder the earth. That which we affirme is this. And we appeale vnto the conſcience of the reader, whether wee ſpeake the truth or not. Firſt we prooue that the offices of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Doctors, Elders, &amp;c. are perpetually to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the Church, becauſe the Lord hath appointed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14765:9"/>them to bee members thereof, Romans 12.6.7.8.<note place="margin">M. Cart 1. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply pag. 140. 141. Counterpoiſon Anſwere to Briges ſlanders.</note> And becauſe Saint Paule writing vnto Timothie, maketh the retaining of them in the Churche of Chriſt, not arbitrarie matters, left to the diſcretion of the Church, but a commaundement which is to bee kept inuiolable, vntill the appearing of the Lord Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we affirme that our Sauiour Chriſt, did eſtabliſhe (Mathew 18. theſe wordes, Tell the Church) this Gouernment of his houſe by the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Paſtors, Doctors and Elders: In that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs, when a brother doth not profite by the degrees of priuate admonition which hee there mencioneth, that wee ſhould acquaint the Church with his offende: Tell the Church ſaith hee. By the Church in this place, wee ſay, that either the whole multitude muſt bee ment, or ſome one man, as the Biſhoppe, Chauncellour, &amp;c. or els the Elders ioyned together, with the Paſtour and Doctrour if there bee any. Nowe you will not ſay, that a man ſhould goe and ſeeke remedie at the whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude when his brother offendeth him. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-ſide, if you ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the Church in this place, is ment ſome one man in the Church, and ſo goe tell the Church; ſhould bee,<note place="margin">The phraſe of ſpeach alſo that on man ſhould be taken for the Church, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable.</note> goe tell one man in the Church, as the Biſhoppe or Chauncellour: The expoſition is diuers vvaies prooued to bee falſe. Becauſe the degrees of proceedings, which our Sauiour. Chriſt ſetteth downe, dooth ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it. For wee are commaunded from a priuate reproofe of our brother between vs and him, to riſe vnto an admonition before one or two witneſſes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14765:10"/>and ſo from two or three, not to come backe again, to make his fault known before one witneſſe, as the Biſhop or Chauncelour, but before many, vz. the Church gouernors, as before is ſet downe. And in this ſpeeche tell the aſſemblie of Church, wee ſay that our ſauiour Chriſt, pointing out by the ſpirit of propheſie, the gouernement of the elderſhip vnder the goſpell, doth allude vnto the forme of the Iews, gouernment in their Sinagogues, vnto whom who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer gaue not eare, was accounted as an heathen or a publicane.</p>
               <p>This M. Bancroft, is the ſum of that which wee affirme out of Math. 18. when you can bring any thing againſt this expoſition of the place, you ſhall be anſwered by the aſſiſtance of God: And it ſhall appeare, whenſoeuer you or yours, dare abide the publike triall of your cauſe, that there are not onely many that affirme this but alſo many that wil proue this to bee moſt true. In the meane time, wee refer the matter vnto the conſcience of the reader, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you and your vpholders, in expounding tell the church, to be, complaine to the Biſhop or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour, that is, tell one man in the Church, or wee which interprete the ſame to bee, tell the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of the Church: to wit, the Paſtor, Doctor, and Elders ioyned together, beeing not one but many, doe peruert the meaning of the ſcripture: and as his iudgement in theſe things ſhall be conuinced, ſo let him account of you and vs accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14765:10"/>
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFT page 9.</bibl> They had ſay theſe men in their ſinagogues, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prieſts, we muſt haue in euery pariſh our paſtors, they their Leuite, we our Doctors, they their rulers of their ſinagogues, we our Elders, they their leuittical treaſurers, we our Deacons.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>And what can you ſay againſt this ſaying of theirs? if it be falſe, why doe you not confute it? your abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie indeed to diſprooue the afternoon you ſhewe in that you leaue it as you found it. And that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may perceiue what madnes it were, for you to go about to weaken any part heereof, I will brieflie note out the places, wherein theſe offices are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned both in the olde and new teſtament.</p>
               <p>Firſt then for the offices of Prieſtes and Leuites, Numb. 16 9.10, and Deut. 33.9.10. and there you ſhall ſee the Prieſts and Leuites ſo diſtinguiſhed, as although they were both of them to teach Iaacob the iudgements, and Iſraell the lawe, yet was the Prieſte alone to put incenſe before the face of the Lord: Now vnder the new Teſtament, anſwerable vnto the Prieſte and Leuite: there is the Paſtor and the Doctor,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4 11.12.</note> and both of them appointed for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together of the Saintes, by the worke of the miniſterie, yet both of them diſtinguiſhed in their ſpeciall ſubiects. The one of them to attend [<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 12.7.8.</note>] vpon the gift of teaching, the other vpon exhortation, the one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in an eſpeciall fort, [<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 12.8.</note>] indued with the word of knowledge, the other with the word of wiſedome. Concerning thoſe, who in the new [<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 12.15. &amp;c 18.8.</note>] teſtament are called the rulers of the Sinagogue, the ſpirit of God in the old, nameth them [<note n="d" place="margin">2. Chro. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>] the Princes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14765:11"/>or the chiefe of the families: who although they were not of the tribe of Leui, yet were they appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the cauſe and iudgements of the Lorde, as well as the Prieſtes and Leuites themſelues. In like manner,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 5.17. Rom. 12.8. Act. 20.28. 1. Cor. 12.28.</note> there are Elders in the newe Teſtament, bearing a diſtinct office from the Paſtor and the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and yet appointed to rule &amp; ouerſee the houſe of God by vertue of their owne proper function. Laſtly, as vnder the lawe, wee finde Church trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, vnto whoſe cuſtody,<note place="margin">1. Chro. 26.20 28 2. Chro. 31.13.15.</note> the dedicate thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſacrifices, and the maintenaunce of the Leuites were committed: So in the kingdome of Chriſt vnder the newe couenaunt, are Deacons appointed:<note place="margin">Act. 6.2.3. Rom. 12 8.9. 1. Tim. 3.6.</note> whoſe office is neither to medle with the word and Sacraments, nor yet with the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the houſe of God, but onely to attend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the goods of the Church, and the right diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of them to the vſe of the poore, &amp;c. I omit heere, that as the Gebonites and the Nethinimes, were imployed about the inferior and baſer offices of the temple and tabernacle, ſo the holy ghoſt hath appointed Church ſeruaunts and widowes, to the ſame purpoſe vnder the Goſpell. Heere by good reades thou ſeeſt, that not onely wee, but the holie ghoſt alſo ſaith, thoſe thinges concerning the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, hoth vnder the new and olde Teſtament, which Maiſter Bancroft is not able to: gaine ſay with any colour of truth. And yet it were, ſeaſon that either his anſwere, or his conſent ſhould: be had.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14765:11"/>
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>M. BANCROFT.</bibl> This forme of gouernement, they cal the tabernacle, which God hath appointed, the glory of God, and of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, the preſence of God the place which he hath choſen to put hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> name there, the courte of the Lord, and the ſhining forth of Gods glory.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>Although I deny not, but the true gouernement of the Church by the Elderſhippe, might haue the moſt of theſe titles truly attributed vnto it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the viſible Church vnder the new Teſtament is adorned: yet the moſt of thoſe names which you ſet downe, being ſomething inſolent and ſtrange, I make no doubt, but all modeſt writers would ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from them: Eſpecially, knowing how ſubiect this cauſe in our time is, vnto the godleſſe cauils of ſuche, as care not what they write to the diſgrace thereof. And becauſe you haue ſet them down with out any authority: for mine owne part, I can no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe thinke of them, then of the brood of your owne ſlaunderous ſpirite, whereunto you can find no couert vnder the wings of your aduerſaries, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue produced your witneſſes, to prooue them none of yours, I will in this point alter mine opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and it ſtands you vpon to cleare your ſelfe. That which followeth in your Sermon, doeth manifeſt both your ignorance in the cauſe, and alſo that you haue ſo acquainted your tongue and pen with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes, that you are a ſtranger vnto the wordes of veritie and vprightnes: your wordes are theſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14765:12"/>
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFT page 6. line 13.</bibl> VVhere this eccleſiaſtical Synod is not erected, they ſay Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is not performed: the office of Chriſt as he is a King, is not ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged: in effect, with out this gouernement, we can neuer attaine to a right and trewe feeling, of chriſtian religion, but are to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe,<note place="margin">Luke. 19.27.</note> who ſay of Chriſt, we wil not haue this man to raigne ouer vs.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>As though we deſire eccleſiaſtical Synods, to be erected in euery congregation, and pariſh, or that we make no difference, betwene a Synod, which is a meeting of al the miniſters, and elders, if occaſion ſhould require, (or more properly of ſome choiſe miniſters and elders) in a whole prouince, or more generall, and the Elderſhippe: which containeth the gouernors, to wit the Paſtors Doctors and elders of one only congregation. The reader may ſe what a meet man you are to be an inueigher againſt the elderſhip, whereas you knowe not what it meaneth, and whether a Synod and an Elderſhip be al one or not.</p>
               <p>Where this forme of eccleſiaſtical gouernement is not erected, there indeed we ſay, that Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance concerning the regiment of his church is not wholy obſerued: but that his whole ordinance is wanting, where there is a faythful teacher we neuer as yet affirmed. And therefore if by your generall ſpeach (that wee ſay Gods ordinance is not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp;c.) you meane that we denye any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to be where the gouernement by the Elderſhip is not eſtabliſhed, you doe but followe your owne humor, that is beare falſe witneſſe againſt the truth, and thoſe that profeſſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>The office of Chriſt as he is a King, is boath to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14765:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>teach and to gouerne his church by his own lawes. Our Biſhops doe profeſſe them ſelues to robbe the church of the ſcepter of gouernement, which they haue tyranuouſly wreſted to them ſelues, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we truly ſay, that they ſuffer Chriſt to haue but halfe a kingdome at the moſt, vnder their juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that we feare ful ſore againſt their wills: we grant indeed, that many congregations in the land, doe enjoy, Chriſt Ieſus raigning among them, by the ſcepter of his word, and wee doe day and night according vnto our weake meaſure of faith, heartily thanke our God for this bleſſing, and beſeeche him from the bottome of our hearts, to ſhew mercy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſoueraigne Queene Elizabeth, vnder whoſe peaceable gouernment, we are partakers of ſo ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable a treaſure. Yet notwithſtanding; it is too well knowen, what a ſtraunger, the ſauiour of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde is to the moſt part within our lande, becauſe the voyce of his goſpell is neuer effectually heard among them: and ſo wee may truly ſay, that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt as he is a king, is no wiſe acknoledged vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> juriſdiction of our Biſhops in many places of our land. Againe, we do ſo thanke the Lord for the enjoying of his Goſpel preached, as we ceaſe not, humbly to intreate his majeſtie, that leeing hee hath vouchſafed vs the lauour to bee of his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, it would alſo pleaſe him, that wee may bee ruled by the offices and lawes of his owne houſe. For what hath the Temple of God to doe with the gouernement and ſtatutes of the kingdome of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt? And we doe proteſt that wee will giue him no reſt, vntill hee hath vouchſaued to heare our ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14765:13"/>euen in this point. And yet in the meane time, we doe acknowledge his office as he is a king: and doe profeſſe our ſelues without this Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which wee labour for; to haue attained vnto ſome right and true feeling of chriſtian religion; though not to ſuch a meaſure, as we hope to reach vnto, whenſoeuer the Lord ſhall graunt vnto vs the vſe of his holy ordinaunce, which wee ſo earneſtly deſire. This may ſerue M. Bancroft for a ſufficient confutation of your looſe and vnbridled tongue; which are not aſhamed to publiſh that without this gouernement we holde, that men can neuer attaine vnto a right and true feeling of religion: we haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore affirmed the contrary, &amp; are able to proue the contrary.</p>
               <p>For wee holde that thoſe 3000. ſoules which in one day were added vnto the Church at Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Act. 2.41.</note> before the Elderſhip was eſtabliſhed among the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, had a true feeling of religion: wee ſay the ſame of the Church of Creta,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> euen before euer Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ordained elders in euery citie among them. The like iudgement wee haue of the church of England, at this day. But as the ſpirite of God recordeth, that notwithſtanding theſe Churches of Ieruſalem and Creet, had a true feeling of Chriſt, yet it behooued them to ſubmit themſelues, according vnto Gods ordinance, vnto the gouernement of the Elderſhip, which [<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 15.4.6. Titus. 1.5.</note>] they enioyed: So ſay wee of our ſelues in Englande, and of all other Churches in our caſe, that although our knowledge and feeling were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great, (as alas it is but too too ſlender) yet are we to be built further and further, and wrought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14765:13"/>by all the holy ordinances of God, leaſt wee be depriued of that inheritance which is to bee had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are ſanctified. And indeed we hold, it is to bee feared, of all thoſe who refuſe to ſtoope vnto the Lord in this point of their obedience, that they haue not as yet felt a right, what true religion meaneth. Therefore, we warne them to enter into their own ſoules, and examine what true ſence they haue of the glory of God, and his fauour towardes them. And as for the moſt of them, that are enemies vnto this gouernment of Chriſt Ieſus, it were to be wiſhed, both in regard of the Church, and common wealth, that their very liues and conuerſations, did not ſhew them, to be either meere Atheiſtes or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and prophane men, that onely content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to haue godlineſſe in their monthes, though their hearts haue denied the power thereof, and are ſo farre from the true feeling of Chriſtian religion, as D. Bancroft is from true and vpright dealing, who ſaith, that we account all thoſe, amongſt whom this Eccleſiaſticall Sinode (as he calleth it) is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, to ſay of our ſauiour Chriſt, we wil not haue this man to raigne ouer vs. The which ſpeech, how vntrue it is, may appeare by that which is alreadie ſpoken. As for the concluſion, which in the latter ende of this page hee alledgeth out of the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Diſcipline, I wiſh with all my heart, if it pleaſe the Lord, that neither hee nor any other ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the cauſe, may feele the waight thereof.</p>
               <p>Whereas in this place,<note place="margin">page 9. line. 26.</note> you would ſeeme to make the Demonſtration of diſcipline, to be the fountain whence you haue deriued the moſt of the thinges
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14765:14"/>hitherto diſcuſſed, the reader is to make no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that ſpeech of yours, then to marke it vppe, vpon the ſcore of your vntruthes: for you ſhall find no ſuch matter in that booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFT page 10. ſect. 2. &amp; 3.</bibl> There was neuer ancient father (as I thinke) ſince the Apoſtles time, that did thus expound the place, Mat. 18. Beſides there hath bin a diuers gouernement from this, vſed in the Church euer ſince the Apoſtles time, and theſe men doe confeſſe, that this gouernment long before the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Nice began greatly to decay and that ſince the ſayd counſel,<note place="margin">T. C.</note> it was neuer heard of in the world, vntil theſe their times.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>They muſt needs be childiſh, and abſurd fathers, that ſhould expounde the place, according vnto your interpretation. The reader hath ſeene, that you haue alleadged your owne comment and not ours. Neither do we runne vnto fathers when we would try the truth, but vnto the ſcriptures themſelues. And yet wee thankefully acknoweledg the helpes, which their labours haue affoarded vnto vs, but ſo as wee held it a maine point of popery to holde that a place is not well interpreted, becauſe no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition can be founde in the writings of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. Beſides, we account your breſt for no librarie, wherein al the interpretations of the fathers vppon this place may be ſene. Chriſoſtom (if that were any thinge vnto the truth) doth expound tel the church, to be,<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. vpon Math.</note> tel the gouernors of the Church, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth in a manner al that wee affirme.</p>
               <p>We know Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rephes to haue bin in the church, euen in the Apoſtles times,<note place="margin">3. Iohn. 9.</note> and wee are aſſured he could neuer be gotten out of it, ſince the firſt hower
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14765:14"/>that he ſet footing therein. And therefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not greatly maruel, though euen in their time, there had bin a diuers gouernment, from this of the lords appointment, which we labour for. For euen in the Apoſtles time, the miſtery of iniquitie beganne to worke. But for al this,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.7.</note> wee would haue you prooue your bolde aſſertion, that euer ſince the Apoſtles time, there hath bin a diuers gouernment from this, and when you haue done, you muſt vnderſtande, that the queſtion betweene vs is not ſo much, de facto, as de jure, not ſo much whether there was a diuers gouernment &amp;c. as whether that diuers go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement was lawfull or not.</p>
               <p>We muſt needs confeſſe indeed, that not onelie this gouernement of the Church, but alſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points of greateſt waight in religion, fell to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay long before the counſell of Nice: But that M. Carthwright, or any man els of iudgement hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that this gouernement was neuer heard of, ſince the ſayde counſell, vntill theſe our times, it is an impudent vntruth. You quote T. C. on the margent, but neither name the page, nor the booke where hee ſhould affirme this which you woulde ſeeme to publiſh vnder his name,. The reader is to marke this is an other of ſhifte, which is ſo much the more ſhamles, as you ground your next ſpeech vppon it, as vpon a matter graunted you without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14765:15"/>
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFT page 10. &amp; 11.</bibl> A very ſtrange matter if it were true, that Chriſt ſhould erect a forme of gouernment to continue vntil his comming, and that the ſame ſhould neuer be once put in practiſe, for the ſpace of 1500. yeares, or at the leaſt (to take them at their beſt) that the gouernment &amp; kingdome of Chriſt ſhould then be ouerthrowne, when the diuinity of his perſon the honour of his kingly authors, &amp;c. was eſtabliſhed at the counſel of Nice.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Let the reader marke this for another of your ſhifts.</note>And is it not alſo a ſtrange caſe, that you wil erect a building of your owne ſtuffe, and workmanſhip, and then cal your auditors, to gaze and wonder at the abſurd deformitie of it. Why? there are non but your ſelfe, and ſuch as you are, that affirme this go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement to haue wanted execution, for the ſpace of 1500. yeares. Neither doe we holde or thinke the gouernement and kingdome of Chriſt, to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne at the time of the counſel of Nice. And you haue in this point, giuen your ſelfe the ſhamfull lye, in the 100. page of your Sermon, where you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge that M. Cartwright doth affirme this elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to haue bene moſt flouriſhing vnder Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the Emperour, by whome the Nicene councell was called. I referre the reader vnto the place, and &amp; wiſh you, though you cannot be gotten to leaue forging of vntruthes againſt vs, yet for your owne credit ſake, not to forget the chiefe ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime of your profeſſion: which is, that it behooueth a lying tong to be joyned with a good memorie.</p>
               <p>We doe not ſay, that the gouernment and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt is wholly ouerthrowne, where the Elderſhip is wanting, and therfore, your ſpeech ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that way, doth rather point out the eſſentiall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14765:15"/>all qualitie of your nature, then any concluſion of ours.</p>
               <p>And admit it were true, that the Elderſhip lay in the duſt, at the time of the Nicen counſel, and was neuer heard of in Chriſtendoome from that hower vntill this latter age. Will you conclude thereof, that therefore it is not nowe to bee receiued? that is Poperie. For the holy men there met togeather, ſuffered many other ſubſtantiall and moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie points of doctrine to be buried, as they had bene long before their time, and were neuer in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner taken out of the ground vntill this latter age. And all that the fathers decreed at Nice, beſides the matter of Arrius, which is but one branch of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on farre from a perfect confeſſion of faith, let any man read their Cannons as they are ſet downe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Ruffinus,<note place="margin">Ruffi. lib. 2 cap. 6.</note> or in the firſt Tome of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and hee ſhall finde my wordes to bee moſt true.</p>
               <p>The errours concerning free will, and mans abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to fulfill the lawe, deriued from Iuſtin the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, and Irenaeus was at this time in ſome ripenes, and yet the Nicene Councell tooke no order with theſe thinges, as it may appeare by their writinges, who liued in the ages following. And though Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine long after, againſt the pelagians &amp; els where gaue free-wil a deaths wound, yet notwithſtanding, wee knowe, that euer ſince the Apoſtles time, in a manner it flouriſhed euery where, vntill M. Luther tooke the ſword in hand againſt it. And by Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Bancrofts reaſon, the Papiſtes defending free-will, againſt Maiſter Luther, helde the better part.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14765:16"/>For it may be thought a ſtrange matter in the ſight of M. Bancrofts popiſh eyes, that eyther mans. free will and abilitie to fulfill the law of God, ſhoulde in our time be thought erroneous, and to annihilate the vertue of Chriſts kingdome and prieſthood, or that the Lord in his word ſhould eſtabliſh a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie doctrine therunto, for his Church to follow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his comming againe, whereas the ſame was win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at, or buried, when by all mens confeſſion, the diuinitie of our Sauiour Chriſte,<note place="margin">Theſe are M. Bantro. words.</note> the vertue of his prieſthood, the power of his office as he is a prophet and the honour of his kingly authority, was ſo god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo learnedly, and ſo mightily eſtabliſhed againſt the Arrians in the Councell of Nice, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So that if this argument bee good and forcible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church gouernement, it is alſo powrfull to ouerthrowe the maine point of our iuſtification by faith, beſides manye other corruptions which were paſt ouer, yea and eſtabliſhed at that councell, which is iuſtly accounted one of the ſoundeſt, that the ancient times can affoord vnto vs. Paphnutius alone, was enforced to ſtande vp againſt the whole Sinode in the cauſe of the marriage of Miniſters, which notwithſtanding, he (being a man himſelfe indued with the gift of continency) ſo defended, that hee would not haue him that were a Miniſter being vnmaried,<note place="margin">Zoromen lib. 1 cap. 23.</note> euer after to be joyned with a wife. Theſe things, and many ſuch like, together with M. Bancrofts iudgement of vs, pag. 11. and his treatiſe of the going out of falſe Prophets, page 11.12. &amp; 13. I overpaſſe, becauſe I would be briefe.</p>
               <p>Concerning the 4. cauſes yelded by him, why
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14765:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>falſe prophets goe out into the world, we denie not but the contempt of the true gouernours of the Church, ambition, ſelfe loue, and couetouſnes, do cary many away from the ſinceritie of the truth: nowe whether theſe doe beare ſway in M. Bancroft and out Biſhops, let the worlde indge. The place of Ierom (touched pa. 14.) vnto Euagruis ſhalbe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpoken off.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFT page 17.18.19. &amp; 20.</bibl> But the ſtory of Aerius is moſt pertinent, to ſhew that ambition dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth men to be falſe Prophets. Epiphanius doth report it thus in effect. Euſtathius and Aerius ſtroue one againſt another for a Biſhopricke.<note place="margin">Lib. 3. Tom. 1. haereſ. 75.</note> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius obtained it, whereat, Aerius began to repine, and grewe to bee a ſciſmatike, defending that by the word of God, there was no difference betweene a Prieſt and a Biſhop. Hee vſed the ſame arguments that now are vſed of theſe that maintaine his opinions. As that the Apoſtle wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſometimes to prieſts and deacon, ſometimes to Biſhops and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons ſhoulde thereby ſignifie, that a Biſhop and a prieſt is al one. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, Aerius after due tryal, and examination, had by the learned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who then liued of his arguments and ſleight, was by the generall conſent, of the Church overthrowne, and condemned for an heretick. And to this day there was neuer any but heretikes, and ſuch lewde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that condemned the callings of Lord Biſhops for Antichriſtian.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>There is nothing brought in here out of Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, but it hath beene anſwered long ſince by M. Cartwright,<note place="margin">M. Cart. 2. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply 1. part. page 68.</note> and ſhewed to be the reaſon of Pighius an Archpapiſt, againſt M. Wicklieffe and the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes, it beſemeth M. Bancroft very wel to borow the weapons of ſuch a champion, to fight againſt the truth. But firſt M. Bancroft, I woulde knowe what you can ſay againſt the perſon of Aerius, touching the truth which he defendeth, we wil deale after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: you anſwere that Epiphanis reckoneth him
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14765:17"/>vp amongſt hereticks, and ſo you account of him. Wherevnto I reply, that Ierome dealeth with vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius after the ſame meaſure, becauſe vigilantius held it vnlaweful to pray for the dead,<note place="margin">Ierom ad Ripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium &amp; contra vigi. antium.</note> to worſhip the dead bones, and reliques of Saints, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded marriage, to bee preferred before virginnitie. Wherein Ierome (though otherwiſe a godly man) doth rather bewray his immodeſt raſhnes, then any wiſe diſcredit Vigilantius with thoſe that know the truth. The ſame is to be ſayd of Epiphanius and Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. And indeede, for any thing that Epiphanius and Pighius hath brought, or you can bring againſt him, he was an honeſter man, than either Euſtathius his competitor, or Pighius and D. Bancroft his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futors. Hee is ſaid indeed to be an Arrian, but that could neuer be prooued as yet, and it was rather an action of ſlander, rather commenſed againſt him by his proud enemies the Biſhops, then any true accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, whereof he can be prooued gilty. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde,<note place="margin">Looke Danaeus in Auguſt. de haereſ. cap. 53.</note> in the whole Eccleſiaſticall ſtory, written by theſe that liued after him, that euer there was any crime of hereſie layde to his charge, whereas Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius his ſchoolefellowe and aduerſary, is recorded by them, as alſo by Epiphanius, for a knowen and famous hereticke.</p>
               <p>Touching Epiphanius, though I will not call his name in queſtion, yet thus much I may truly ſpeake of him, that he was (as the lerned know wel enogh) ſo beſotted with the corruptions of the times wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he liued, that his credite alone, is not of ſufficient authority to paſſe ſentence againſt Aerius. For the proofe hereof, the reader is to vnderſtand, that hee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14765:17"/>condemneth Aerius for a black heretike, as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee helde it vnlawfull to pray or to offer anie thing for the dead, as in that hee defended a Biſhop and a Prieſt as M. Bancroft ſpeaketh, to be of equall authoritie. As for Auguſtine, whom you bring with Epiphanius againſt this poore heretike, hee rather followeth the receiued opinion, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his own iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, according vnto truth.</p>
               <p>This much touching the perſon of the man, as for his hereſie, if he had noe other then thoſe which Epiphanius layeth to his charge, and eſpecially this of the aequallitie betweene a miniſter and a Biſhop, the ſpirit of god giueth him a plaine diſcharge from all ſuſpicion, either of hereſie or yet of error. For the word of God teacheth vs, that to bee a teaching El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (which you retaining your popiſh cuſtome, call a Prieſt) is nothing els, but Epiſcopein,<note place="margin">1. Pet 5.1.3.</note> that is to be a Biſhoppe or an ouerſeer. And Chriſt Ieſus forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his Miniſters to haue any ſuperiority one ouer another. Now, when Pighius, D. Bancroft,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.25.</note> or any other Romane Papiſt or Proteſtant, ſhall be able to aunſwere theſe and the like reaſons, they may then haue good leaue with open mouth, to cry out vpon Aerius for his hereſie. Otherwiſe, in condemning that ſentence, whoſe premiſes they are not able to infringe, they doe nothing els but deny the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which in this, and many other pointes, is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Bancrofts faſhion of diſpute. For what els doth he in alleadging, that men haue condemned Aerius for an heretike, whereas neither he nor they, can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the reaſons whereupon Aerius his concluſion is grounded. And if Aerius his opinion, was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14765:18"/>then that the worde of god made no difference betweene a Biſhop and a miniſter; as maſter Doctor here ſetteth downe, I cannot thinke but vppon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aduiſement, he wilbe concent to reuoke the raſh ſentence, which he hath pronounced againſt him, leſt thereby he doe not only ſtrike at Ierome; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at the Archbiſhop,<note place="margin">M. Bancroft is ſo haſty to wound his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, as he alſo ſtriketh himſelfe and his friends.</note> and al others, that are of his ſide in England at this day. For Maſter Bancroft I thinke wil not ſay, that a Biſhop is ſuperiour vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter by the worde of god, then howe wil he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere Ierome in the places quoted by him ſelfe page the 14. who ſayth that in the Apoſtles time,<note place="margin">Ierom. ad Eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gri.</note> there was noe ſuch difference betweene them, and that this prerogatiue that one miniſter ſhould be aboue a nother, is grounded vpon humane cuſtome, &amp; not vppon the ordinance of God. And after this ſorte doe our Biſhops account of the preſent Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, which they holde vnchangeable, onely as long as it ſhall pleaſe her maieſtie and the ſtate. If M. Bancroft be of an other judgement, we ſay that he condemneth not Aerius aloane, but euen Ierome and our Biſhops for obſtinate hereticks, &amp; we craue his anſwere vnto the place of Ierome. Nowe if hee be of Ieromes minde, I would gladly learne of him and Epiphanius, where they learned to condemne men of hereſie, for gainſaying ſuch things in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as haue no other original and ground then the conſtitutions of men. For if it was not an hereſie in the Apoſtles time (as Ierome telleth vs it was none) to holde a miniſter and a Biſhop to be of aequal au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, it can be non at this hower, neither coulde it beat any time ſince the age, wherein they liued.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14765:18"/>For noe man can be nowe accounted an hereticke, for defending that which had been ſound, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique doctrine in the Apoſtles time.</p>
               <p>Now that either we or Aerius ſhould conclude, the aequallitie of miniſters becauſe the Apoſtle wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſometimes vnto Prieſts and Deacons, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnto Biſhops and Deacons, For mine owne part, I neuer heard of the reaſon before. The reader is to make no other account of it, but as a teſtimony of Maiſter Chaplaines acquaintaunce with our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. And I beleeue it I ſhould aske either him or Aerius, where they finde that the Apoſtle hath written vnto Prieſtes any otherwiſe, then they are contained vnder the name Biſhops) and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, I ſhould put them both to their ſhifts.</p>
               <p>Where he ſaith, that Aerius was condemned for an heretike, by the conſent of the whole Church, after due triall and examination of his arguments, by the learned fathers then liuing, it is as impudent an aſſertion, as euer he vttered. And I maruell, that hee bluſheth not to publiſh ſuch windy ſtuffe vnto the view of the world in this learned age. Indeede, if Aerius had no other reaſons, then that which wee haue already heard, the learned fathers of his time were verie ſimple, that would ſtand in the triall and examination of ſo groundleſſe a ſuppoſition. I am ſorie to heare you ſo farre gone in the heat of your impatiency, as you ſhould denie the ſuperioritie of Miniſters to haue beene againe-ſayde, and their Gouernement accounted Antichriſtian, by anye ſince the time of Aerius, ſaue onely by heretikes and ſuch lend perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14765:19"/>Do you account the Waldenſes to be heretikes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Do you account M. Wickliffe,<note place="margin">And I pray you what account you of the refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med churches.</note> M. Iohn Huſſe, and M. Tindale to be heretikes or lend perſons? The godly haue them in other maner of eſtimation. And yet M. Carthwright and others haue long ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued theſe men to be vnreconcilable aduerſaries vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hierarchie, and ſhewed that they beganne no ſooner to ſtand againſt the Pope, but they alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred with the Biſhops, whoſe callings, that they doe belong vnto the Antichriſtian kingdome, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by this reaſon: whereunto if you will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the credit of your maſters, I would wiſh you to anſwere.</p>
               <p>Thoſe offices and callings are Antichriſtian, with out which, all forme of Gouernements are perfect, ſaue onely the gouernment of the kingdome of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt which in no wiſe can want them.</p>
               <p>But ſuch are the callings of Lord Archb. and Bb. as all forme of gouernements may be perfect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, ſaue onely the Antichriſtian kingdome, where in no caſe they can bee miſſed. For the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment both of the Church and common welth, can well ſpare them, and bee neuer a whit the more vnperfect. Therefore, the callinges of Archb. and Biſhops, do only belong vnto the kingdom of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt. If you do reply M. Bancroft, that the moſt learned; and the moſt zealous of the fathers, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in theſe latter times, haue taken vpon them the callings of Biſhops and Archbiſhops, you do therby nothing els, but offer to produce your witneſſes to ſweare that the concluſion is not true: And therfore as I haue ſaid, ſo I admoniſh you again, not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14765:19"/>yourſelfe in ſo gaineleſſe a labour. But if you will ſtand our Biſhops in any ſtead, deale againſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the propoſition or aſſumption, otherwiſe the burthen of the concluſion will lie vpon them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will or no.</p>
               <p>Your diſtinction of the cleargy and layity facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">To the 24.25.26.27. pages.</note> we acknowledge not: For wee maintaine ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther factions nor ſciſmes. If there bee any Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or great men, that deſire to be inriched with the patrimonie of the Church, wee wiſhe them better mindes, and pray that they may bee diſapointed of their expectation. Yet we ſee no more reaſon, why our Biſhops and Chaplaines ſhould liue vpon the ſpoile and robbery of ſoules, then Noble men and Gentlemen ſhould bee maintained by ſacriledge. For we holde, that both ſorts, in ſo doing, do bring the price of bloud into their houſes. But it is moſt intollerable, that they who would bee taken for Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites and gouernours of the holy Temple, ſhould haue a ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in this treſpaſſe. You haue ſtreined your conſcience to far I feare me, in going about to make vp the credite of Biſhop Coopers admonition to the people of England.<note place="margin">Page 24.</note> A large conſcience I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hath along hand, to reach a diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a far of. Let the reader conſider the place.</p>
               <p>If you ſet downe any thing that is Annabaptiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or Popiſh, it were meete you ſhould confute it,<note place="margin">Page. 25.</note> leaſt the ſimple auditors ſhould take it for your own doctrine, rather then other mens errours. Nowe I come to that part of your Sermon, where you deale concerning the triall of ſpirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14765:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D: BANCROFT page 33. lin. 26. &amp; pag. 34. lin. 19. &amp; 41. lin. 17.</bibl> The popiſh falſe Prophets wil ſuffer the people to try nothing, but teach them wholly to depend vppon them. The giddy ſpirits woulde haue men to be everſeeking and ſearching. The meane therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt both theſe extremities I holde to be beſt. And this it is, that when you haue attained the true grounds of Chriſtian Religion, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly built by a liuely faith vpon Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> being incorporated into his miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eal body, by your baptiſme, and afterwards nouriſhed with the Lords Supper: you then content your ſelfe and ſeeke no farther, &amp;c.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>It is well known, that wee allow neither popiſh, norgiddy ſpirites, no nor yet ſlaunderous and lying ſpirites. As for the rule of the popiſhe falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, you haue ſquared your doctrine page 43. juſt according vnto the ſame, as the reader ſhal perceiue in the proper place.</p>
               <p>You haue plotted vs out heere ſuch a meane, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two extreamities, as they muſt needes bee meane Chriſtians, that will go no further, then the reſting place which you haue ſet downe for them. I will not ſay heere that the Papiſtes will graunt the miſerable people vnder them, leaue to goe thus far, which is true: but this I will ſay, that this doctrine of yours, tendeth wholly to remooue an able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie out of the Church, and ſo conſequently, to robbe the people both of the ſcepter of Chriſts go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, and alſo of his word. For if the people neede no more, (nay, if it bee vnlawfull for them to go any further) then to bee baptiſed, and after they haue attained vnto the true groundes of Chriſtian religion, &amp; are engraffed into Chriſt, to receiue the Lordes ſupper; to what vſe ſerueth the preaching of the word? And to what end ſhould the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.9.10.</note> that the word of God, ſhould dwell plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14765:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>among Chriſtians, and pray that our loue maye abound more and more in knowledge,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.6.</note> and in al fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that we may diſcerne things that differ, that we may bee pure, and without offence vntill the day of Chriſt, filled with the fruits of righteouſnes, &amp;c. If you could once M. Bancroft, bring this meane of yours to take place: then indeede might you place readers inſteed of Preachers, ouer the people with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controllement, and ſay that they need no other teaching, becauſe they are baptiſed, engraffed into Chriſt, and fed with the heauenly foode exhibited vnto them in the Lords Supper: and what need they more? For Tertullian ſaith,<note place="margin">Page. 42.</note> that we need not be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, after we haue apprehended Chriſt, nor in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue, after we haue receiued the goſpell. But a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable teacher are you, that in ſuch ſort doe open a windowe vnto the deuill and mans corruption, to breake faith into all impietie and wickedneſſe. For how ſhall either the rage of ſathan againſt vs, or the rebellion of our owne corruptions within vs, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, but by that mighty ſcepter of Chriſts word preached, euen vnto vs that haue receiued the firſt fruits of the ſpirit. If you had euer knowne what it had bene, to receiue Chriſt truly, and to retain him being receiued, you would neuer haue endeuoured to ſeduce your auditors, in this monſtrous &amp; popiſh ſort. But becauſe the light of your owne conſcience doth tell you, that chriſtians cannot containe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues within this priſon, wherein you haue ſhutte them: You ſet downe a good ſupply of the want of teaching, if men would deſire to be reſolued in anye matter of doubt: your owne wordes, or rather your
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14765:21"/>popery I will ſet downe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>D. BANCROFT page 42. &amp; 43 line 24.</bibl> God hath bound himſelfe vnto his church of purpoſe, that men by hir good direction,<note place="margin">Councels.</note> might in this point (that is in maters of dout) be relieued: to whoſe godly determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in maters of queſtion, her dutiful children, ought to ſubmit themſelues without any curious or wilfull contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Neither can I ſee, nowe that popery is banniſhed, and the trueth of chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is godly planted amongſt vs, why in theſe dais, we ſhuld not attribute as much to the decrees of our learned fathers in their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſemblies, as other men in times paſt, of as great iudgement as wee are, haue done.</q>
               </head>
               <head>ANSVVERE.</head>
               <p>You account the Papiſts to be falſe Prophets, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will ſuffer the people to trie nothing,<note place="margin">Page 33.</note> but teach them wholly to depend vppon them: you do wel in it. But if this touching cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, be not to ioin hand with them, in the point wherin you pretend to bee their aduerſary, &amp; if this be not to teach men to beleeue, as their mother the church doth let the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der iudge. The Biſhop of Rome, deſireth no more to bee graunted vnto him, for the authoritie of his councels, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue ſet down in expreſſe terms. And if the Lorde hath bound himſelfe by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vnto his Church of purpoſe, that men ſhould be directed therby: I would demaund of you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this promiſe was, that the Church ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them vnto truth, or vnto errour. If you ſay vnto truth, otherwiſe it were no promiſe, I demand then how the Church can erre? For either the Lord muſt breake his promiſe, if hee hath made any, or els the Church cannot erre in the direction of her dutifull children. Now if you ſay, that the Church cannot erre, the reader knoweth what account to make of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14765:21"/>you, if ſhe be ſubiect vnto errors, to what end ſhould we ſtand to her determination in matters of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, any further then we are aſſured, that her decrees are according vnto the word. Now, if it be lawfull for vs (otherwiſe our bondage ſhould bee intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to trie whether her determinations bee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the word, and to reiect them, if they bee otherwiſe, to what ende doe you carry vs from the ſure foundacion of the worde, vnto the vncertaine and vnconſtant voice of the Church? ſurely, if you would know what I conceiue of you, for this, &amp; the like points of doctrine in your Sermon, my opinion is, that you are not far from a cloſe papiſt, how vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo euer you ſpeake againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and whoſoeuer they were, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> allowed your Sermon to be publiſhed, they may iuſtly feare, leaſt the Papiſts doe ere it be long, make too great aduantage that you haue bene ſuffered to preach and to publiſh many grounds of popery vnreprooued, vnder the profeſſion of the goſpell. The Church of God we reuerence, to bee wilfull in ſtanding againſt her, or any member ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we holde it vnlawfull, but that men ſhould ſtand in matters of queſtion vnto her determination, as vnto the vndoubted voyce of God, ſhe hath no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to require any ſuch obedience at our hands.</p>
               <p>I dare ſay for you, that you are vexed at the verie heart, that any thing eſtabliſhed in the Conuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on houſe ſhould bee called in queſtion, when you prooue that aſſembly to be lawfull, and the learned fathers (as you call them) there met, to bee true Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and not rauening wolues, wee will promiſe to giue greater reuerence vnto their degrees. Poperie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14765:22"/>is ſo banniſhed from amonge vs, that by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of thoſe learned fathers, you dare in open Pulpit, and publike writinges, iuſtifie many points thereof.<note place="margin">Anſwere to the 46.47.48.49. pages.</note> It is not onely lawfull but neceſſary, that all men, of what ſtate ſoeuer they bee, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, yea, &amp; compelled by the Magiſtrate, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto true religion. 2. Chron. 14.12, &amp; cap. 34 31.32. 2. Kings 11.17. Nehem. 9.38. &amp; 10.29. This we doe willingly confeſſe: Howbeit, we hold it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to ſubſcribe in that forme that our Biſhops do exact at our hands. Your reaſon that ſubſcription is lawfull, therefore the Engliſh, or the Auguſtane ſubſcription is lawfull, is no other then if I ſhould ſay, that religion is good, therefore the popiſhe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is good. But of all other points in your booke, I cannot but greatly wonder, that you ſeeme to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the ſubſcription vnto the Auguſtine confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſilenceing of thoſe that would not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto it.<note place="margin">Page 47. lin. 24</note> You are not ignoraunt I thinke, that the ſaide confeſſion is vnſound, in the point of the Lords ſupper, which hath ſet Germany on fire theſe many yeares. As for the ſubſcription which in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is required by ſtatute, our men haue beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ready to yeelde vnto it. But the learned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whereof you ſpeake, ſeeing that by the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcription, they could haue no aduantage againſt the truth, haue coyned a new one of their own, which we hold vtterly vnlawfull, becauſe it requireth our conſent vnto the popiſh hierarchie, vnto the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cripha, and many other corruptions. The which courſe of theirs, becauſe they are not able to iuſtifie, therefore haue you done well, to finde out a waye,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14765:22"/>whereby they may eaſilie determine of any queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or difficultie mooued vnto them. So that now, if we deny to ſubſcribe vnto that, which againſt law they require of vs, vntill we be ſatisfied in the douts wee make, whether it may be lawfull for vs to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the proud and ambitious ſuperioritie of one miniſter aboue another, the appointing of ignorant and godleſſe men vnto the Miniſterie, the croſſe in Baptiſme, the prophanation of that Sacrament by women, with other manifolde abuſes, which we are vrged to approoue, their anſwere may be according vnto your rule, that they beeing the learned fathers of our Church, haue in their lawfull aſſemblies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that this ſubſcription ſhould bee called for, and they ſee no reaſon, why popery being now ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, &amp;c. wee ſhould not attribute as much vnto their decrees, as other men in times paſt haue done.<note place="margin">Looke M. Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft in the place ſet downe before.</note> And ſo if we were dutifull children, we would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues without any wilful contradiction vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their godlie determination: ſeeing the Lord hath by his promiſe, tied himſelfe vnto them, being his Church for this purpoſe. Now, if we ſhall reply any thing againe, as being vnſatisfied by this reſolution, wee are preſently cried out vppon, as being giddie Spirites, and men that cannot bee content with any good order eſtabliſhed by lawe, and approoued by our betters, euen ſuch as gaue their bloud for the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the truth. And thus in ſtead of anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our reaſons, they inuent ſlanders againſt vs, and fall out with our concluſion, according vnto Maſter Bancrofts manner of dealing.</p>
               <p>Whereof as I haue often before admoniſhed the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14765:23"/>reader, ſo nowe I haue ſpecial occaſion to put him in minde of the ſame concerning his dealing with vs touching the booke of common prayer, and the point of her maieſties ſupremacy. Wherein he ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth 20. pages for the moſt part,<note place="margin">From the 50. to the 72. pages.</note> wee ſhewe diuers corruptions to be in that booke, wee ſet downe the particulars, as baptim by weomen, croſſe in baptime ring in matriage, appropriating of garmentes to the vſe of religion, and groſſer coruptions, as Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme, where the booke maketh Michael to bee a creature,<note place="margin">The Collect on Michaels day.</note> and addeth vnto the word, as pſalme 14. in which place, 3. verſes, that is the 5.6.7. are added vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the text, more then euer the holy Ghoſt penned in that pſalme, with other grieuous corruptions, which I paſſe ouer. Nowe howe doth M. Bancroft thinke you deale for the credit of the booke, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering theſe particulars? hee toucheth not one of them, but firſt of all hee telleth his auditors, howe glad al the churches in Europ were at the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of religion,<note place="margin">Page. 15.</note> in the beginning of her Maieſties raigne, And for our partes wee wiſh them confuſion that doe not reioice at it.<note place="margin">Page 53. From 54.58.</note> Secondly hauing ſet down what paines was taken in reforming the booke hee bringeth in diuers teſtimonies of godlye learned men, to prooue that the booke is in a manner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpotte, or wemme, whereby what doth hee els but fall out with our concluſion. Wee charge the booke with diuers particular corruptions, we bring our proofes,<note place="margin">Page 61.</note> he is not able to anſwere them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our concluſion wil ſtand firme, that the booke is corrupt. The general commendations of all the men in the world is not able to cleare it, when it is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14765:23"/>not denied to containe many groſſe particular falts. Thirdely he falleth a quarreling with a newe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion booke, preferred in parliament,<note place="margin">Page 62.63.</note> the yeare 86. and caueleth diuers waies againſt the ſame. As y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it had bin diuers times altered, that it mencioned not the ciuil magiſtrate in the firſt edition, and that it doth not tye the miniſter to any ſet forme of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp;c. Al which points, I omit as friuolous, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly cauils not to be ſtood vpon.</p>
               <p>Laſtly he falleth to his olde bias, that is to plaine ſlaundering,<note place="margin">Page 67.</note> and affirmeth that one of our reaſons whie wee holde the eſtabliſhed gouernment of the church of England to be Antichriſtian, is becauſe the ciuil Magiſtrate is made a Pope amongſt vs, and that we cal her maieſties ſupremacie vnto queſtion. wherevnto wee anſwere no otherwiſe, then Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah did Sanballat.<note place="margin">Nehem. 6.8.</note> It is not done according vnto theſe wordes that thou ſayeſt, but thou faineſt them of thine own hart. Looke whatſoeuer prerogatiue in eccleſiaſtical or ciuil cauſes hee or any man liuinge can truly attribute vnto the ciuil magiſtrate, wee do the ſame. Concerning the preheminence in ciuill cauſes there is no great queſtion he wil ſay between vs,<note place="margin">Page. 71.</note> only in eccleſiaſtical matters we aſſume vnto our ſelues ſaith he, that authoritie which by right is the magiſtrats. This ſlander is general, we deſire the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular proofe of it wee cannot anſwere generalles, hee repheth that the magiſtrate by lawe is to haue whatſoeuer priuiledg the pope at any time had with in this land by vſurpation,<note place="margin">Page. 70. lin. 3.</note> what will hee conclude hereof? Not I hope that the magiſtrate is to haue the power of remitting ſinnes, and diſpenſing with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14765:24"/>the law of God, which the Pope by vſurpation had in times paſt within this kingdome? Her Maieſtie wee know, deteſteth al ſuch prerogatiues from her hart. But what is it that he requireth to be graunted vnto the ciuil authoritie, which wee yelde not moſt willingly? The power to eſtabliſh godly eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal lawes, and conſtitutions amongeſt the ſubiects? wee are ſo far from denying this, that wee holde it intollerable that our Biſhops, and the conuocation houſe, ſhould intrude their ſubſcriptions, aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and cannons vpon the ſubjectes, whereas no ſuch things can be warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by ſtatute. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as hee ſayth, that wee claime vnto our Presbiteries the ordinary authoritie to make al lawes, conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ceremonies of the Church, it is moſt falſe. Al that wee affirme in this point, is noe more then her majeſtie voluntarily yealdeth in all ſuch caſes. when the queſtion is whether ſuch or ſuch a caſe be ſtatute law or not? whether doth M. Bancroft think her majeſtie or her learned councel in the lawe, as her judges, Solliciters, Atturneis, &amp;c. to haue grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt skill in the deciding of this matter? he knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well enough, that her Majeſty in all ſuch points, will be directed by that which her aforeſaid lawiers do prooue to be law and equitie, and yet thinketh her royall prorogatiue no whit diminſhed thereby. In the like caſe then, we ſay that the true gouernors of the church are meeteſt to direct her majeſty what lawes and ceremonies are moſt lawfull, expedient, &amp; neceſſary, for the right gouernment of the church And we ſay, that as her majeſtie in worldly matters, is to giue eare vnto the Lawiers which haue skill in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14765:24"/>that facultie: ſo, in the matters of God is ſhe to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh nothing in the church, but that which the true miniſters and true gouernors (if they may bee had) ſhall ſhew vnto her to be according vnto the worde of GOD. And yet all this while wee make not the gouernours of the Church to haue power to enact laws, we leaue that authoritie vnto her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and the Parliament, vnto whoſe hands the Lord hath committed it. This indeed we affirme. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that her majeſty and the Parliament are bound to eſtabliſh and erect amongſt their ſubiects, al ſuch lawes and ceremonies, as the true Miniſters of the word, ſhall prooue by the Scriptures of God, to bee meet and neceſſary for the gouernment of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and houſe of the Lord, within this kingdome: And that they are bound to ſee, that no forme of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or Church-gouernment be in force amongſt the ſubjectes, but that alone which by the word of God may bee prooued lawfull, and ſo that they are bound to ſee, that the Church of God bee clenſed and purified of all Idolatrous, popiſh, ſuperſtious, and ſuperfluous gouernment and ceremonies. And furthermore we ſay, that they are to prouide by law that all perſons, both Miniſters and others, doe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues without contradiction, vnto all ſuch things as ſhall bee godly eſtabliſhed in the Church. Whether this bee M. Bancroft to weaken or call into queſtion her Maieſties prerogatiue in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical cauſes, let the reader determin. We would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſire him to iudge, whether her Majeſtie be well vſed at your hands, which call her a petty Pope, and ſay that ſhee vſurpeth the ſame authority in cauſes,<note place="margin">page. 68. lin. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14765:25"/>Eccleſiaſticall with in her dominions, which the pope did in times paſt. Had we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued, much leſſe publiſhed any ſuch things, wee had worthily ſmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for it. Your anſwere heere will be, that you did bring in this reaſon, to ſhew the weakenes of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins arguments againſt the Biſhops. Let Martin in other points anſwere for himſelfe. The caſe of her Majeſtie and our Biſhops are not alike: He prooueth our Biſhops to be petty Popes and vſurpers, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it not. And therefore you onely addreſſe your ſelfe to ſhew what a rebellious and abſurd concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hee hath made by the like kinde of reaſoning as you ſuppoſe. And where his minor truly aſſumeth our biſhoppes to be vſurpers and petty Popes, you falſely and ſtanderouſly charge her Maieſtie to bee an vſurper and a petty Pope. Wee are not ſo haſtie to ſhead bloud as you are, otherwiſe, this your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulnes is ſo heinous, that I could eaſily ſhewe that there were no other waye of deſence for you; but in the acknowledgement of your raſh boldnes, (to giue your doings no worſe tearmes) to flie vnto her Maieſties clemency.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>TOVCHING SCOTLAND.</head>
               <p>VVE anſwere, that we deſire not the Elderſhipp to be planted in the Church of England,<note place="margin">From the. 72. to the 78. page</note> becauſe Scotland or Geneua enjoyeth the ſame, but in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as Chriſt Ieſus the head &amp; king of his church hath commaunded it to bee therein. And therefore we admit the gouernment of no church vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to be the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>e of that which we deſire, but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14765:25"/>only that regiment which is ſet downe in the word of God, the perfection whereof if any Church hath attained vnto, wee rejoice with them, and deſire to be pertakers of ſo great a bleſſing, in the Lods good time. But as for any thing that is amiſſe (if there be ought) either in Geneua or Scotlande, wee labour no more to haue that eſtabliſhed in England, then we doe to haue the great abuſes that raigned in the Church of Corinth, or Galatia to be imitated. The ſlaunder which you haue raiſed,<note place="margin">Page 75.</note> both againſt the Kings Maieſty there, in giuing out, that he is a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enemy vnto the preſent gouernement eſtabliſhed in his kingdome, and watcheth but his time to ouer throw it, and alſo againſt the godly miniſters of that realm, in making them traitors vnto their ſoueraign, Heaue to be anſwered by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: and I dout not, but you wil in time be forced to anſwere the iniury, that you haue offered vnto that godly and noble King o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and alſo vnto the whole Church, with in his dominion.</p>
               <p>But let it bee graunted, that the true Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours in Scotland, behaued themſelues rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly towards then Prince, which yet is moſt falſe, what is that to the Church gouernment which they enioly? Doe you thinke it a good ſeaſon to ſay, that the Archbiſhop is a Traitour, therefore the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke is gilty of Treaſon: You can not deny, but Thomas Becke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was a traitor, ſo were diuers others that haue beene Archbiſhops of Canterbury, but I truſt you will not therefore attaint the Archbiſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricke of treaſon.</p>
               <p>Browne a knowne Sciſmatike is a man very fit to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14765:26"/>be one of your witneſſes againſt the Elderſhip.<note place="margin">Page 75. lin. 29</note> His entertainment in Scotland was ſuch, as a proud vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly man deſerued to haue. God giue him and you repentance, if it be his will, otherwiſe, you ſhall make and hard reckoning both of you, before the iudgement feate of Ieſus Chriſt, for the ſlaunders which you haue raiſed vp againſt the gouernement of his kingdome heere vpon earth. Your calender deceiued you for it was not the Parliament of the yeare 88. where of hee wrote,<note place="margin">Page 76. lin. 4.</note> but of another held Anno 86. or before.</p>
               <p>If any thing be written amiſſe in any of the books that you mencion,<note place="margin">Page 78.</note> wee haue nothing to doe therewith. Bring our owne aſſentions, and you ſhal be anſwered. We holde it altogether vnlawfull for Miniſters and Church officers to deale in any ciuil cauſe, much more, to depoſe Princes, and therfore our attempts that way are not to be feared. Looke you,<note place="margin">Page 79.</note> &amp; your maſters vnto thoſe thinges, who arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat vnto your ſelues, that preheminence, which is in deede dangerous vnto the throne of the magiſtrate and thinke Parliaments and lawes cannot bee halfe orderly kept and enacted, without Lords ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>Your feare,<note place="margin">Page 80. lect. 3</note> that whatſoeuer hath bene done or written in forraine Countries, is laboured to haue execution with vs at home, is but the ouerflowing of your gall. The diſeaſe is daungerous, and you may one day aunſwere for your diſtemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rature in his preſence, before whome the imaginers of euill againſt their brethren, ſhall haue their reward.</p>
               <p>We holde indeede,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> that the Magiſtracie is gods ordinance bee he a good or a bad,<note place="margin">Page 81.</note> an heathen, or a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14765:26"/>Chriſtian, that is called thereunto: ſo that the right of a Chriſtian and an heathen Magiſtrate, within his dominions is the ſame. You that hold the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, profeſſe your ſelfe not to bee a ſubiect for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, as the Apoſtle commaundeth, but for ſome other reſpect. So you would bee very duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full belike, if you were vnder an heathen Prince.</p>
               <p>Miniſters wee ſay, are not to deale in ciuill cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">Page 82. lin. 27</note> and therefore in that point wee aſcribe vnto the Magiſtrate, both Poteſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> juris &amp; facti: that is, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to make lawes, &amp; to execute them. If there ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie difficultie (as often as it commeth to paſſe) of that which is agreable vnto the law of God, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that are controverted, then indeed it is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters dutie to enforme the Magiſtrate of the mind of the Lord: wherein hee doth nothing els, but (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondere de jure) ſhewe what the will of God is, that the magiſtrat may (ſtatuere de facto) pronounce ſentence accordingly.</p>
               <p>For Eccleſiaſticall matters, it is the word of God onely, that therein hath (poteſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> juris) the power to determin, what is acceptable in the ſight of God, &amp; the Miniſter ought to haue the knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that he may declare the ſame, both vnto Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and people. The Church officers alſo are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God, to execute all eccleſiaſtical maters. And if you ſhould attribute this power vnto the magiſtrate, the imagiſtrate might iuſtly account of you as you are. For will you haue the Magiſtrate to preach the word, adminiſter the Sacramentes, take the charge of watching ouer the maners of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and diſtributing to the pore within his pariſh? or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14765:27"/>will you haue him to viſite the ſicke, comfort the weake, ordaine miniſters, diſcuſſe controuerſies in religion, &amp; exerciſe the church cenſures, by excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, &amp;c. And yet theſe are the only maters which wee account eccleſiaſticall, &amp; wherein alone we hold it lawfull for church officers to deale, other puniſhments of malefactors as impriſoning, fining, or any mulct y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> toucheth the life, body or goodes of men, are only to be reterced to the Magiſtrates, who beare the ſword for that purpoſe. Our Biſhops v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping this ſword, doe ſhewe that they and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, and not wee doe labour to bring and maintaine confuſion in church &amp; common wealth.</p>
               <p>You exhortation both vnto people and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,<note place="margin">Page. 85.</note> that the one ſhoulde avoide, and the other puniſh heretical ſpirits, we imbrace withal our harts. Being ready to ſhewe, as our writings haue done at large, that your errors, corruptions, idlenes pride, ambition, ſlaunders, and vntruthes, vttered againſt the truth, hath not only (as dayly experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs) begotten and nouriſhed the lamentable ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, which euery where raigneth in this land, but alſoe called for the wrath of God to fal vppon vs, becauſe ſuch vnruly and wicked ſpirits as you, are tollerated in the holy miniſterye amongeſt vs.<note place="margin">Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> You are now come to the gathering vppe of your ſtanders and vntruche, into an heape in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your ſermon, leſt the readers and auditors ſhoulde forget, that you are an impudent ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. And therefore that you may incenſe the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates againſt vs in one place, eſpecially you rake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp after this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:14765:27"/>Hir Majeſtie is depraued, hir authority is impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and greate dangers are threatned.<note place="margin">Page 57 to 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> M Doct. think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> belike that wee are maintainers of the hierarchy</note> Ciuil gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is called into queſtion: princes pretogatiues are curiouſly ſcanned; the intereſt of the people in kingdomes is greatly aduaunced, &amp; al gouernment generally is pinched at &amp; comemened: The Church is condemned, the auncient fathers are deſpiſed, your preachers are defaced, and yet theſe men are tollerated.</p>
               <p>Whereunto I anſwere with the wiſe man, that the lying tonge ſlayeth the ſoule,<note place="margin">Pron. 12.6.</note> and that the very wordes of the wicked lye in wayte for blood, but the mouth of the righteous wil deliuer them. And ſo wee doubt not, whenſoeuer wee are araigned for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe heauy accuſations, but that wee ſhalbee deliuered from this bloody tonge. The reader kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that (as a noble Emperour ſpake in the like caſe) if it be ſufficient to accuſe, no man can be innocent. Nowe if he hath theſe aduantages againſt any of vs, let him ſet down his particulars, and name the man, or his writings, and he ſhalbe anſwered. Otherwiſe we make no other account of ſuch Epiſtrophaes &amp; homoioteleutaes,<note place="margin">page 88. line 4.</note> then of the barking and dogge Rethorick, of ſome profane Lucian or god leſſe Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirie. It is no news for vs to haue our legs &amp; thighs deſired to be broken.<note place="margin">Ioke. 19.30.</note> The reader is to remember, that this was the Iewes requeſts vnto Pilate concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our Sauiour Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore wee are not to thinke it ſtrange, that M. Bancroft is guided by their ſpirit whoſe place he ſupplieth. But this wee are to knowe, that neither he not his maſters ſhal do any thing againſt vs, but that which the Lord our
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14765:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:14765:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14765:29"/>God hath long ſince determined, and therewith by his grace,<note place="margin">Act. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> wee hope to be right wel contented.</p>
               <p>In ſtead of arming his hearers with reaſons out of the word againſt vs, whome he accounteth ſect. maſters and falſe Prophets, hee commeth off, after his wonted manner, with idem peridem, leauing his auditors in as great doubt as they were before: And ſaith, that the doctrine of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is pure and holy:<note place="margin">Page 89. lin. 27</note> the gouernement thereof, both in reſpect of her Maieſtie, and of our Biſhops is lawfull and godly: the booke of Common praier, containeth nothing in it contrary to the word.</p>
               <p>Her Majeſties gouernement, he knoweth well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough we call not in queſtion. He and his patrons, haue corrupted the doctrine of our church, &amp; as for the hierarchy &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon booke, when he hath made vp y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holes which I haue alredy ſhewed to be in both (beſides the vncureable woundes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other men haue diſcouered) he may build ſomthing vpon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, which if he doe not, his maner of diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in crauing and begging the matter in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie will in a while growe to bee a common prouerbe. If we were ſuch vnreaſonable men, as we would find ſalt with matters that are blameleſſe: his exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that priuate men would take heede,<note place="margin">page 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 89.</note> and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate take puniſhment of vs, would carry vvith it ſome vvaight. But in aſmuch as both the Magiſtrate and people ſee, that vvee haue cauſe to ſpeake, and perceiue that out aduerſaries can doe litle, if they cannot ſet a faire face vpon a crackt cauſe, wee feare not any great hurt, that his tongue can worke vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14765:29"/>And the very ſame account doe we make of his ſpeach, where hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Page 94.</note> that wee vſe the ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes for the ſoueraigntie, of our Presbiteries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prince, in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, that the Pope doth for his principallitie in the ſame, and we anſwere as the Papiſts do him.<note place="margin">This is VVhit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifts quarel, and anſwered long ſince.</note> But theſe thinges (as hee ſaith) hee cannot ſtand to prooue at this time, onely hee thought it neceſſary to aduertiſe his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of it, that they might the better beware of ſuch kind of ſpirits. Take his aduantage who liſt.</p>
               <p>We care not how little a doo we haue at the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> and therefore we meane not to take any great aduauntage againſt your tongue, any further then your bluſhing may be for the clearing of the truth. The reader will thinke you worthy to be marked in the forhead, according vnto the Romaine lawe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you prooue this which you haue ſo confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe. Though, as it ſhould ſeeme, you haue a commiſſion, to vſe your tongue and pen at your pleaſure, yet you cannot blot out the light of mens reading &amp; knowledge. We are known to be ſo out of amitie (in this caſe eſpecially) with all Romaniſts, and you truly accounted to be ſo neerly allied vnto them, that wee deſire no other weapons to ſtrike downe the hierachie, then M. Luther, and M. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine haue vſe to ouerthrowe the Romaine chaire and her miniſters.</p>
               <p>How often ſhall it be tould you,<note place="margin">Page 95.</note> that we would haue no ciuill matters handled in any eccleſiaſticall meeting? and therfore, that we admit not anything in our aſſemblies, to be decreed againſt the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Princes, any further then Princes may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:14765:30"/>the truth of the word to bee againſt their ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. We are as far from making our owne wils,<note place="margin">Page. 96. 97.</note> to be the rules of other mens liues, or from affirming that what wee ſpeake is the very word of God, as you are from being aſhamed to lie in the face of the ſunne: you haue taken great paines in ſowing the ſeed of moſt groſſe vntruthes: repent betimes, leaſt in the Lords iuſt iudgement, you reape the fruits of your lying tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning M. Cartwright. Page 97. 9S. 100.</head>
               <p>VVE depend not vppon men, Chriſt Ieſus is our onely guide. As concerning M. Cartwright, whome you (to keepe your tongue in vre with your naturall vaine) call our ring leader, wee bleſſe God, that euer he hath vouchſafed vs ſuch an inſtrument to ſtand in the defence of his holy gouernment, and to giue your hierarchie, and your high Prieſte the ſhamefull foile. But we follow him no further, then he attendeth vpon the truth of his God. And in that worke we are not aſhamed to glaine after ſo worthy a man. But what can you lay to his charge? you ſay that hee alleadgeth Cyprian, Ierom, &amp;c. to prooue the equality that ought to be in the miniſters of the word and Sacraments, and that in the ancient times there was no difference betwixt a Biſhop &amp; a Prieſt, but that whoſoeuer was a Biſhop, was a Prieſt alſo: and that they had all equall authority within their own pariſhes, whereas the cleane contrary ſay you, is to be ſeene in their writings.</p>
               <p>Then heauen and earth, bee you iudges in this cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that the mouth of this ſlanderer may be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14765:30"/>Firſt, the place of Cyprian lib. 1. epiſt. 3. calleth him a Prieſt,<note place="margin">Defence 355.</note> whome D. Whitgift would haue to be an Archbiſhop, &amp; the papiſts affirme to be his elder brother the pope. Therefore by Cyprians iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſoeuer was a Biſhop, was a prieſt. Again, Cyprian ſpeaking of the election of a prieſt, by the conſent of the whole people, lib. 1. epiſt. 4. hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſame maner of electing Cornelius, Biſhop of Rome, and calleth his Biſhopricke a prieſthood, lib. 4. epiſt. 2. Nowe,<note place="margin">Tom. 1. Can. lib. 4 epiſt. 9.</note> that Cyprian condemned ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority among Biſhops or miniſters, his ſentence in the counſell of Carthage prooueth it: where hee ſaith, that none of them made him ſelfe a Biſhop of Biſhops, he alſo reprooueth Pupianus, that he made himſelfe a Biſhop of a Biſhop.</p>
               <p>As to Ierom,<note place="margin">2. Reply 1. part pag. 591. Ierom. ad Euag</note> M. Cartwright alleadgeth theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces out of him. A prieſt, that is to ſay a Biſhop, and a little after, the Apoſtle doth plainely teach, that a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and a prieſt are all one. And in another place,<note place="margin">Ad Oceanum.</note> a Biſhop and a prieſt are the ſame: againe although with the ancient fathers, Biſhops and prieſts were al one.</p>
               <p>Now good reader beare witneſſe, whether Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Cartwright hath falſified the ancients or not, &amp; whether this paſt ſhame Doctour, hath not cauſe to ſow vp his lippes for euer opening them in pulpit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. For the confirmation of the equalitie of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp; that the name Biſhop, was common vnto al the Miniſters of the word and Sacraments in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times, thou maieſt adde vnto that which hath bene already ſpoken.<note place="margin">Ignatius ad Smyrnenſis.</note> Firſt the teſtimony of Ignatius which ſaith, that it was not lawful for any to baptiſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14765:31"/>but for the Biſhop. Where then M. Bancroft was the diſtinction, betweene him and the prieſt, or hys ſuperioritie ouer the prieſt? Secondly, that in the time of Gregory the great, prieſtes did ordaine Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and yet this is made one of the eſſentiall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences betweene a Biſhop and a prieſt,<note place="margin">Greg in Euan. a VVhitgift page 387.</note> [a] that a Biſhop may ordaine, whereas a prieſt hath no ſuch authority. Thirdly, that Theod. mencioneth an 150 Bb. which were met, for the election of the Biſhop of Conſtantinople.<note place="margin">Theod. lib. 5. cap. 8.</note> Where all theſe Bb. could bee gotten, if Bb. and Miniſters were not all one, let M. Bancroft ſhew. Laſtly, it would be knowne, what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count M. Bancroft maketh of that notable martyr M. Tindale,<note place="margin">M. Tindales works. pag. 251. b.</note> which ſpeaking of prieſts and Bb. hath theſe words: ther is presbyteros, which ſame is ſaith he,<note place="margin">Acts. 20.28.</note> imediatly after called a Biſhop: and in the ſame place, all that were Elders or prieſts (if they ſo will) were called Biſhops alſo, though they haue deuided the name now. I hope he will not anſwere him, as hee doth Aerius, that this opinion was condemned for an hereſie long ago, and none but heretikes and ſuch leud perſons euer ſince that time held it.</p>
               <p>One thing I doe not a litle maruel at, both in M. Bancroft and all the reſt of his coat, why they rather ioyne with Sir Thomas Moore and the papiſtes,<note place="margin">M. Tindals an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Moore. page. 251.</note> in calling the Miniſters of the word prieſtes, then with M. Tindale, and the moſt ſincere profeſſours in the world at this day, in abrogating that popiſhe name, and vſing the worde Miniſter, or Elder in the ſteade thereof.<note place="margin">Admon. pa. 44.</note> The B. of Wincheſter ſayth, that the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop hath ſhewed ſufficient reaſons againſt T. C. why the Miniſters of the goſpell ſhould bee called
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14765:31"/>prieſts, and all of them are of the ſame opinion, and will not take it patiently if they be gainſaid in it: but what account is to be made of them for this labor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhal learne out of M. Tindale,<note place="margin">page 14. 4.</note> who in his obedience of a Chriſtian man ſayth, that the worde Sacerdos, ſhould haue had another name in engliſh, then prieſt, but that Antichriſt hath deceiued vs with vnknowne and ſtrange termes, to bring vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuperſtitious blindnes, as for the word presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros ſaith he (both in this place, and againſt Moore in the place aboue cited) it ought in Engliſh, to bee tranſlated Elder. This I thought good to admoniſh the reader, leaſt hee ſhould thinke mee in vſing the woorde prieſt, to allowe of that Antichriſtian name. Whether M. Cartwright hath truly alleadged Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius and others,<note place="margin">To the 98. pag.</note> to prooue the vſe and practiſe of the office of Elders in the Church, long after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, becauſe there is nothing but the pawn of M. Bancrofts credite brought to the contrary, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the reader, to examine the teſtimonies vſed by M. Cartwright for that purpoſe.<note place="margin">T. C. 1. reply 145.</note> Eſpecially the place of Ierome vpon Iſaiah, who ſaith that they had alſo the presbitery or elderſhip in the church, and that of Ambroſe vpon the 1. Tim. cap. 5. where he complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that through the pride &amp; ſlouthfulnes of the Doctors, the Elders were worn out of the Church: were it not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> M. Chaplain carrieth his licenſe in his boſome, to ſpeake what hee will, I ſhould wonder that he durſt in open pulpit and writing, deny elders to be in the church long after the Apoſtles time, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing D. Whitgift telleth vs of his owne knowledge, that in the Primitiue Churche, they had in euerie
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14765:32"/>church certaine ſeniors, to whome the gouernment of the congregation was committed.<note place="margin">Whit. pag. 638.</note> M. Bancroft, ſeeth there is no aduantage in granting any part of the truth, and therefore, hee taketh a round courſe, to deny euery thing without more a doo: Take his aduantage thereof who liſt.</p>
               <p>His profanenes,<note place="margin">Page. 98.</note> in calling the Elders, Aldermen, the Lord I feare will reuenge, who cannot abide to haue the officers of his kingdome, derided and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at by any Lucian whoſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Your caueling with the proofes,<note place="margin">To the 100.111.</note> brought in by M. Cartwright, to ſhew the Elderſhippe to be moſt flowriſhing in Conſtantines time, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a proofe, that you retaine your vſuall boldneſſe in out facing the truth. If it bee not a good reaſon to ſay, that becauſe there were infinite numbers of Biſhops and Elders, at the councel of Nice, therefore the Elderſhip was in a flowriſhing eſtate at that time, to what purpoſe, ſhould they be preſent in that ſynod, if they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with the gouernement of the church? If they had to do with the gouernment of the church, the reaſon holdeth moſt forcible, to prooue the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip to be vp vnder Conſtantine. For whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer there is a Church gouernement by Biſhops and Elders, there the Elderſhip is in force. Though wee ſhould graunt,<note place="margin">Page 101.</note> that you deale truly with Euſebius, yet his teſtimony is not a whit the weaker, to proue the gouernment by the Elderſhip, becauſe he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing els, but to ſhew the great appearaunce from all places of the Cleargie men, of all ſortes in that aſſemblie. Eor beit that his onely purpoſe was, to ſhewe this great concourſe of Cleargy men, yet
<pb facs="tcp:14765:32"/>that hindereth not, but hee ſpeaking of Biſhops and elders met at the ſaid Synod, we may thence gather, Biſhops and Elders did gouerne the church at that that time.</p>
               <p>That Biſhoppes had large juriſdiction before the Nicene councel is onely affirmed,<note place="margin">M Cart. 2. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply pag. 557.560. &amp;c.</note> and not prooued by you M. Bancroft: the contrary hath bene ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It is your manner to build vpon falſe grounds, which haue beene long ſince ouerthrone. The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of Metropolitans (or confirming whether you will) at the councell of Nice, hindered not the gouernement of the Elderſhip to be in force. They had not ſuch an vnruly juriſdiction, as the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops doe vſurpe: The fifth Canon of the councell, whereby it is decreed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the diſorders of the church, ſhould bee compounded, at the prouinciall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, &amp; not by that Metropolitans ſhew, what ſmal authority they had. They had but their owne ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages as euery other miniſter had. That which the councell of Nice attributed vnto them, was no more then chiefe place in the meetinges.<note place="margin">Ibid. pag. 562.</note> Aunſwere that which M. Cartwright hath written in this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then ſet downe your bolde concluſion: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, the reader will deride your boldnes, in pitching a campe of torne aſſertions, whereof, not one will be granted vnto you.</p>
               <p>Faine would you I ſee, haue the people not to giue eare vnto vs,<note place="margin">To the 103 104. page.</note> and to that purpoſe you bring vp to them the reaſons, that al Atheiſts haue for them ſelues, whie they wil not embrace the true religion. And that is becauſe the profeſſors thereof cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree among them ſelues. The godly are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<pb facs="tcp:14765:33"/>that there muſt bee ſciſmes in the Church of God, and therefore cannot ſtumble at the diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among vs,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i</note> if they bee any. Wee haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the bleſſed Apoſtle to bee ſo farre from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with any ſaue only in the truth, as we hold our ſelues bound to bid battel vnto at the Angels i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heauen, if they ſtand againſt the ſame. Our breaches would bee eaſily made vp,<note place="margin">Pag</note> if you woulde yeald the Church her right. As for your ſide, it is wel knowne howe little you agree ſaue only in the mayne drift, whereat you muſt al ſhoot, or els you ſhal ſoone fal to the ground. And that is in ſtanding againſt the truth,<note place="margin">Tot 111.</note> &amp; maintaining outragious coruptions. I haue alredy noted, that you in this ſhort inuectiue againſt vs, haue twiſe ſcratched the Archbiſhop by the face, and that in matters of waight.</p>
               <p>The 3. laſt pages of his Sermon, contain nothing in them, but generall exhortations, that the people would cleaue vnto the truth without wauering: the which wee earneſtly entreat all men to doe, as they would bee ſaued in the day of the Lorde: And from our hearts we wiſh (if it be the Lords will) both vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and to all our aduerſaries, and perticularlie vnto M. Bancroft, that immortall crowne of glorie, whereof, he ſpeaketh in the laſt page, deſiring them and him, notwithſtanding to call to minde, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyers,<note place="margin">Page 1</note> nor thoſe that delight in lies, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt gods truth and his church, ſhall euer be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14765:33"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:14765:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14765:34"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
